# Housam Babiker

CONTACT

Department of Computing Science housamkhalifa.github.io University of Alberta, INFORMATION Edmonton, Canada Email: khalifab@ualberta.ca

RESEARCH INTERESTS Research interests include a broad area of Explainable Artificial Intelligence (XAI), Machine Learning, Deep Learning, Reinforcement Learning, and their applications in real-world problems.

**EDUCATION** 

### PhD in Computing Science

Sep. 2016 - Nov 2022

University of Alberta

Edmonton, Canada

• Academic Supervisor: Prof. Randy Goebel Research project: Building self-explainable deep neural network

### MSc in Information Technology

2013 - 2015

University of Alberta

Edmonton, Canada

• Academic Supervisor: Prof. Lau Siong Hoe Thesis title: Design and Evaluation of a Shoulder Surfing Resistant Authentication System.

# **BSc** in Information Technology

2008 - 2011

• Thesis title: Face recognition using local graph structure.

Multimedia University

Melaka, Malaysia

# WORK **EXPERIENCE**

# Graduate Research Assistant

Sep 2019 - Present

Department of Computing Science, University of Alberta

Edmonton, Canada

• Carrying out research on the development of XAI techniques for deep learning at the XAI lab under the supervision of Prof. Randy Goebel.

# Machine Learning Engineer

Dec. 2019 - Present

AltaML Inc.

Edmonton, Canada

- Developed NLP models for legal domains, constructions (e.g., predictive models, semantic search, model in the loop, keyword extraction) and presented the findings to senior executive management.
- Developed NLP models to understand the legal cases in order to segment them in meaningful contexts.
- Worked on models compression to improve the inference speed.
- Provided regular progress reports to manager both verbally and in writing, and turned data into further actionable decisions.

Researcher

Oct. 2018 - Feb. 2019

Department of Family medicine

University of Alberta, Canada

• Developed a tool to extract medical information from Electronic Medical Records.

Research Assistant

2013 - 2015

Information security lab, Multimedia University

Edmonton, Canada

• Research on biometrics, computer vision and image processing.

# RESEARCH ARTICLES

- 11. **Housam Babiker**, Mi-Young Kim, Randy Goebel, SFFA: Softmax For Feature Attribution (submitted). Proceedings of the Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing (EMNLP) (20 pages) 2022.
- Housam Babiker, Mi-Young Kim, Randy Goebel Locally Distributed Activation Vectors for Guided Feature Attribution in COLING 2022(Accepted).
- 9. **Housam Babiker**, Mi-Young Kim, Randy Goebel Neural Networks with Feature Attribution and Contrastive Explanations in ECML PKDD 2022(in press).
- 8. Mi-Young Kim, Shahin Atakishiyev, **Housam Babiker**, Nawshad Farruque, Randy Goebel, Osmar R. Zaiane, Mohammad-Hossein Motallebi, Juliano Rabelo, Talat Syed, Hengshuai Yao, Peter Chun. A Multi-Component Framework for the Analysis and Design of Explainable Artificial Intelligence. Machine Learning and Knowledge Extraction, Special Issue on Advances in Explainable Artificial Intelligence MDPI, 3, pp900-921, 2021.
- 7. Housam Babiker, Mi-young Kid and Randy Goebel. DISK-CSV: Distilling Interpretable Semanic Knowledge via Class Semantic Vector. The 16th conference of the European Chapter of the Association for Computational Linguistics (EACL) 2021. Accepted. April 21-23, Kyiv, Ukraine.
- 6. **Housam Babiker**, Mi-young Kid and Randy Goebel. RANCC: Rationalizing Neural Networks via Concept Clustering. The 28 International Conference on Computational Linguistics (COLING) 2020. December 8-13 Barcelona, Spain.
- Housam Babiker and Randy Goebel. An Introduction to Deep Visual Explanation. Neural Information Processing Systems (NIPS) 2017 Workshop, Interpreting, Explaining and Visualizing Deep Learning. Long Beach, USA.
- 4. **Housam Babiker** and Randy Goebel. Using KL-divergence to focus Deep Visual Explanation. Neural Information Processing Systems (NIPS) 2017 Symposium on Interpretable Machine Learning 2017, Long Beach, USA, (Selected for a spotlight presentation).
- 3. **Housam Babiker**, Randy Goebel, and, Irene Cheng. Facial expression using SVM classifier on salient mic-macro patterns. Proc. International Conference on Image Processing (ICIP), Beijing, China, 2017.
- 2. Abdullah M., Sayeed S., Muthu S., **Babiker H.**, Azman A., and Ibrahim Yousif. Face recognition with symmetric local graph structure (slgs). Expert Systems with Applications. 41(14)6131-61372014.
- 1. **Housam Babiker** and Eimad Eldin Abdu Abusham. Face Recognition Using Local Graph Structure. International Conference on Human-Computer Interaction. Orlando, Florida, USA 2011.

## **TEACHING**

- CMPUT 174: Intro. to the Found. of Computation I Fall 2017 Prof. Jörg Sander and Sadaf Ahmed's teaching assistant (TA) at the University of Alberta.
- CMPUT 414: Introduction to Multimedia Technology, Fall 2019
  Prof. Anup Basu's TA for the senior undergraduate level course at the University of Alberta
- CMPUT 101: Introduction to Computing, Fall 2016

  Prof. Janelle Harms's TA for the senior undergraduate level course at the University of Alberta

#### OTHER TALKS

#### • Research Poster at AI Week

May 2022

Presented a paper entitled "Self-explainable models in natural language processing" at AI Week in Edmonton, Canada.

#### • EACL 2021, Ukraine

Dec. 2020

Presented a paper entitled "RANCC: Rationalizing Neural Networks via Concept Clustering" (Online).

## • EACL 2021, Ukraine

Sept. 2017

Presented a paper entitled "acial expression using SVM classifier on salient mic-macro patterns" (ICIP, Beijing, China).

#### • Reverse EXPO

Feb. 2017

Presented a poster of the "An Introduction to Deep Visual Explanation" article to the audience of diverse background in Edmonton, Canada.

# ACADEMIC SERVICE

- Reviewer for the Journal of Artificial Intelligence Research (JAIR), EMNLP 2020, ICDM 2020, ECML-PKDD 2020,2022.
- Local Arrangement Chair, The 2017 IEEE International Conference on Systems, Man, and Cybernetics. Oct 5-Oct 8. Banff, Canada.
- Maintaining the Explainable AI (XAI) lab website https://sites.ualberta.ca/~amiixai/.

# TECHNICAL STRENGTH

- **Programming:** Python, C++, SQL, Matlab.
- Frameworks: Tensorflow, PyTorch, Keras, NLTK, OpenCV, Scikit-Learn, Pandas.
- Databases: MySQL
- Other: Linux Command Line, Bash Scripting, GitHub, Version Control

# HONORS & AWARDS

- Highest performance on task 4 of the COLIEE competition 2018, Japan.
- GSA Travel Award 2017, university of Alberta.
- Multimedia university research scholar Award.
- Dean List, Multimedia University.
- 2013 Infineon-MMU Technical Poster Session, Infineon, Champion.
- 2014 Infineon-MMU Technical Poster Session, Infineon, Champion.
- 2015 Infineon-MMU Technical Poster Session, Infineon, 1st Runner up.
- Pecipta by Ministry of Education (MOE), **Best of the Best Award**, International Conference and Exposition on Innovation of Institution of Higher Learning, Nov-2013, Kuala Lumpur Convention Centre, Malaysia.
- Pecipta by Ministry of Education (MOE), Gold Award, International Conference and Exposition on Innovation of Institution of Higher Learning, Nov-2013, Kuala Lumpur Convention Centre, Malaysia.
- Korean Invention Academy Award, Malaysia, International Conference and Exposition on Innovation of Institution of Higher Learning, Nov-2013, Kuala Lumpur Convention Centre.

- ITEX Silver Award, Malaysia, Invention Innovation Technology Exhibition (ITEX) 2013 by MINDS.
- WIC- Gold Medal, Seoul, South Korea, World Invention Innovation Contest (WIC) 5-6-June. 2015.
- ITEX Silver Award, Invention Innovation Technology Exhibition (ITEX) 2015 by MINDS, Kuala Lumpur Convention Centre, Malaysia.
- Pukyong National University, South Korea, scholarship for Master of Science (declined).
- Multimedia university, graduate research assistant for PhD, (Declined).
- C++ programming Competition, **2nd Runner up**, multimedia university, Melaka, Malaysia.

Last updated: August 17, 2022